# 哈喽 大家好
Hello everyone
# 上次跟我师父借了这个工具以后
After borrowing this tool from my master last time,
# 我用这个也做了一个凉糕
I also made a Lianggao (cold rice pudding) with this
# 也做出了以前小时候的味道
also made the taste of my childhood
# 现在我拿回来还给他
Now I take it back to him
# 他今天因为这个天气下雨 所以没有出摊
He didn’t go out selling today because of the rain
# 所以我今天特意来看一下他
So I visit him today specially
# 我给你拿点水果来
I'll bring you some fruit
# 这个我拷了50坨
I made 50 lumps
# 一坨平均都有一斤多重 是不是我倒多了哦
A lump weighs one jin (0.5kg) on average, is it because I have poured too much?
# 你舀满了
You poured it full
# 舀得太满了噶
I poured too full?
# 米又买了2袋啊
You bought 2 more bags of rice?
# 啊 拷了2盆啊
Ah, I made 2 pots
# 就是那点
That's it
# 卖2天 卖了就没得了
Sold for 2 days, it ends when sold out
# 哦
Oh
# 那以后都不卖了啊
Then you won't sell it anymore
# 不卖了 这下明年都不卖了
Not selling it anymore. I won’t sell it next year
# 今年他要卖我都不要他卖了
I told him not to sell it this year
# 以前我都是立了秋我就不干了
I used to stop doing it when Liqiu ("start of autumn")
# 立了秋我就不干了
I do it until Liqiu
# 不是 师父你的意思是以后都不干了啊
Master, you mean you don’t do it anymore.
# 啊
Ah
# 那不能说得那么绝对
That can't be said absolutely
# 我不要他卖了
I don't want him to sell it
# 他想着想着就要卖
He keeps thinking about it and then picks it up
# 之前歇了五年没卖 不要他卖了
He already took a 5-year break. I don't want him to do it.
# 街上的人要吃我的凉糕的嘛
The people on the streets always want my Lianggao
# 有人问他嘛 他回来又不得了
Someone asked him, then he came back. Big deal!
# 街上好多（起码不低于20个）人都说你好多年没干了
Many people on the street (at least 20) said "you haven’t done it for years"
# 我就好多年没吃凉糕了
"That's how many years I haven't eaten Lianggao"
# 看嘛 我师父说了今年干了以后都不干了
You know, my master said that after doing it this year, he will stop doing it
# 那不能说得那么绝对
That can't be said absolutely
# 要求大了就整点
I'll make some when the demand is high
# 街坊在呼唤的时候还是要出来摆摊
So when neighbors call, you still have to come out and sell it
# 搞忘记给你说（糖浆）要拿白纱布来沥过
I forgot to tell you to strain it (syrup) to with white gauze
# 2斤糖 才弄得黏稠
2 jin of sugar to make it sticky
# 黏 还是黏
Sticky? It was sticky
# 可以黏不可以清
It can be sticky, but not clear
# 清了你不能改 黏了可以
You can’t change it if it’s too clear
# 过于黏了也不得行
Being too sticky is not good, either
# 以后师父不干了 你的这套工具传给我撒
When master quits in the future, could you pass this set of tools to me?
# 要的啊
Yes
# 我以后把这个担子挑起来
I will pick up this responsibility later
# 师父你今年好多岁了
Master, how old are you?
# 65啊
# 以前你在哪里当兵安
Where did you serve when in the army?
# 辽阳待了9个月 在山东又呆了3年多
I stayed in Liaoyang for 9 months, and stayed in Shandong for more than 3 years
# 呆了3年多啊
Stayed for more than 3 years
# 就是我们很多粉丝说你站得很直
Many of our fans said you stand straight
# 他们都在说你是不是当过兵的 我跟他们说是当过兵的
They are all asking if you were a soldier, I told them that you were a soldier
# 你看我的2块军属牌都在上面得
Look, my 2 military family members certificates hanging there.
# 军属
Military family members
# 那会你好多岁安
How old were you then?
# 那会20岁
20 years old then
# 20岁啊去当兵
Served as a soldier at 20
# 那会调皮
I was naughty then
# 这个在部队里党和国家教育多好
In the army, the party and the country educated me well
# 很多人安以前可能是有点调皮
Many people used to be a bit naughty
# 随便哪个 摸都就要跟你干起（打架）
Anyone you bumped into could have a fight with you
# 现在就可以 随便啥子都和和气气的
Now is better, whatever is calm and nice
# 给人家犁过田 喂过牛 还卖过肉 做过屠夫
I plowed the fields for others, fed the cows and sold meat, I was a butcher
# 看来当兵可以让一个人思想变好
It seems that being a soldier can make a person think better
# 怎么说呢 我这个年纪肯定是去不了
How should I put it? I must be too old to become a soldier
# 小时候是挺想去的
I wanted to be a soldier when I was young
# 但是很多原因吧
But for many reasons
# 当兵真的是这样子
It's really like this as a soldier
# 以前还是3年噶
It was 3 years before
# 以前我是4年
I served for 4 years
# 最早是4年啊
4 years at the earliest
# 4年义务
4 years conscript
# 嗯
Yeah
# 要得 师父
Yes, master
# 就在这里吃午饭嘛
Right here for lunch
# 我回去还有事
I'm still going back
# 以后下次再来看你
I'll see you next time
# 好
OK
# 如果你确实是不做这个了
If you really don't do this
# 到时候我来接着干
I'll continue to work then
# 啊 要的啊
OK
# 走了
I am leaving
# 好 要的
OK
# 好 慢走你
OK, take care
# 嗯
Yeah
# 你不送不送 下着雨的
Don't see me off, it's raining
# 你慢走
Take care